<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An enquiry into the vision of the slaying and rising of the vvitnesses and falling of the tenth part of the city: with a post-script concerning the controversie about the duty of allegiance, occasion'd by our late revolution.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 102 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45910</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing I219A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R221618</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99832912</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99832912</idno>
            <idno type="VID">37387</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45910)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 37387)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2187:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An enquiry into the vision of the slaying and rising of the vvitnesses and falling of the tenth part of the city: with a post-script concerning the controversie about the duty of allegiance, occasion'd by our late revolution.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 37, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed in the year, MDCXCII. [1692]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With errata at foot of p. 37.</note>
                  <note>Copy tightly bound.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Dr. Williams' Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Revelation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Restoration, 1660-1688 --  Biblical teaching --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:37387:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ENQUIRY into the VISION OF THE <hi>Slaying and Riſing</hi> OF THE WITNESSES, And <hi>Falling</hi> of The Tenth Part of the <hi>CITY:</hi> WITH <hi>A POST-SCRIPT</hi> Concerning The Controverſie about the <hi>Duty</hi> of <hi>Allegiance,</hi> oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion'd by our Late Revolution.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the <hi>YEAR,</hi> MDCXCII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:37387:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:37387:2"/>
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <p>THE Attempts hitherto to Expound the Viſion of the ſlaying and riſing of the WITNESSES, have proved ſo unſucceſsful, as may well heighten the general Prejudice against Prophecies, to be pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar against the Expounding that Viſion. Yet I having fixed the Time of the expiring of the 1260 days on ſuch Reaſons as ſeem to me very cogent, and which make the ſlaying and riſing of the Witneſſes at the end of thoſe Prophetick days, peculiarly to concern this Nation, and the falling thereon of the Tenth Part of the City, to reſpect our preſent Times, and ſo to be of great import to us to be rightly underſtood, I cannot excuſe my ſelf from making my Expoſition publick, tho' I am ſenſible of a greater Prejudice againſt it than that mentioned.</p>
            <p>For to make the Reſtauration here in the Year 1660 to be the ſlaying the Witneſſes, and thereby the Party that was then prevailed againſt, and have ſince continued Diſſenters to be the Witneſſes, muſt ſurely be very ſurprizing to the Church of <hi>England</hi> Party, who reckon her the Chief of the Reformed Churches. But the Diſcourſe it ſelf does, I hope, yield ſufficient Reaſon for my ſo doing, and to leſſen the Prejudice againſt it, I ſhall here add, That all of the Diſſenting Party are not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be reputed Witneſſes, nor all of the Oppoſite Party are therefore to be excluded from being Witneſſes. For many may upon various motives and occaſions be fallen in with that Party which is the Witneſſes, and yet not be of the Spirit of Truth,
<pb facs="tcp:37387:3"/> ſo as to be really of them. And likewiſe many, whilſt involved with the Oppoſite Party, may keep their hearts ſo aright with God, in promoting the Truth, ſo far as the ſtate and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances they are in do admit thereof, as in ſome meaſure to act the part of Witneſſes, and againſt the politick Intereſts of that Party, which they cannot, or are not yet required of God to free themſelves from Communion with. Men therefore are not ſo much to be judged of by the Party they hold Communion with, as by the part they act in ſo doing. For they may ſo have <hi>the Kingdom of Heaven within them,</hi> as indeed to perform the duty of Witneſſes, whilſt, as to Outer Communion they conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue of the oppoſite Party. And it ſeems by that ſaying, <hi>Come out of her my PEOPLE, that ye be not Partakers of her Sins, and that ye receive not of her Plagues,</hi> Rev. 18. that the People of God may upon a worſe Account continue in Outer Communion with the Babylonian or Antichriſtian Party, but then it appears alſo, how perillous is their ſo doing.</p>
            <p>The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſefulneſs of my Expoſition will be a further leſſening the prejudice againſt it. For it appearing thereby that the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration was the ſlaying the Witneſſes, we ſee then, That the Zealous Party of the late Times had more cauſe to excite their Zeal, than their Adverſaries were aware of, and alſo that the ſame Party continuing ſince Diſſenters, had the like for their Separation, being that in both they have but done the Duty of Witneſſes; which will much leſſen the great prejudice againſt them, and Jealouſies of them, and the Diviſions and Troubles occaſioned thereby; and alſo will make us ſenſible how needful it is, to have all Cauſes of Enmity aboliſhed, all Partition-walls broken down, that the Sheep of the good Shepherd may unite in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to one true Chriſtian Fold under Him, by <hi>obſerving all thoſe Things which he hath commanded,</hi> (without corrupting the Truth with the Doctrines and Precepts of Men) and ſo may <hi>find Him always with them to the end of the World.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the riſen Witneſſes having now attained to the Philadel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phian
<pb facs="tcp:37387:3"/> State of having <hi>an open Door ſet before them which no man can ſhut,</hi> may further advance that State among us, by becoming united in Brotherly-kindneſs and Chriſtian Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, with thoſe with whom they have been hitherto at va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riance, and ſo the falling of the Tenth Part of the City, and the ſettling us in that State, may be together fulfilled with us.</p>
            <p>And it appearing by my Expoſition, that our late Revolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was in order to the introducing ſo happy a Change, as that ſignified by the Fall of the Tenth Part of the City, it gives us a proſpect of a happy Iſſue out of our preſent Troubles, however they be yet prolonged; and alſo gives us to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that we are acceſſary to their continuance whilſt we are reluctant againſt that Change, or are wanting of a due further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and promoting the ſame. And being that my Diſcourſe tends only to undeceive us, in our too highly prizing our ſtate hitherto, in order to the preparing us for a much happier ſtate approaching, ſuch as muſt needs be deſirable to every good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, and ſurely ſhould not be unwelcome to others alſo, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering that our preſent Diſtractions have ſo little Proſpect of Settlement otherwaies, I hope it's a ſufficient Apology for the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom I have taken, in making out the Truth of my Expoſition.</p>
            <p>I have added a Poſt-ſcript concerning the great Controverſie about the Duty of Allegiance, occaſioned by our late Revolution, Which being a wonderful Work of Providence, deſigned for the great end I have mentioned, I have endeavoured to clear it from that ill Imputation which ſome blemiſh it with, who by conteſting the Rightfulneſs and Legality of it, raiſe the ſaid Controverſie. Enough hath been ſaid to vindicate the Legality of it, according to the Conſtitution of the Government, though that be needleſs for juſtifying it, when it appears to be a work of Providence proceeding from Gods Will and Concurrence to it. And if all Changes of Government are thus wrought by Him, as will appear by my Poſtſcript, than much rather ſo are ſuch Changes as this, which is of ſo good tendency as diſproves its
<pb facs="tcp:37387:4"/> proceeding from the <hi>Evil One.</hi> But ſome have ſo little Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of God's Providence in governing the World, that they will not admit of it but with ſuch limitation as it next to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding it. <hi>His changing Times and Seaſons, and removing Kings and ſetting up Kings,</hi> they will not allow of, otherwiſe than in a legal courſe, unleſs by expreſs Nomination or Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and ſo, manifold great Changes which God makes in the Governments of the World, <hi>to the end that Men may know that the moſt High Ruleth in the Kingdom of Men and giveth it to whom he will;</hi> being that, <hi>Becauſe they have no Changes, therefore they fear not God,</hi> are excluded by ſuch Men from being the Works of Providence, though they are more peculiarly ſo than thoſe they allow to be ſo, and more ſerve God's end in making ſuch Changes.</p>
            <p>But the ſo limitting the Providence of God in his working Changes in the Governments of the World, proceeds not only from a ſlow Belief of what Scripture does teach thereof, but alſo ſignifies little Inſight into the State of the oppoſite King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of Chriſt and the Devil in the World; the conflict between which, and the decree of God to put the Powers of the one un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Feet of the other, are the main occaſions of his making ſuch Changes, by which he purſues the fulfilling his decree, as well as awakens in men a fear of him. I have therefore given ſome brief Account of the Riſe and State of thoſe Kingdoms in the World, driving on to that happy Iſſue of the great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict between them; whereby the great works of Providence for accompliſhing the ſame, may be contemplated with better Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, than blindly to be cenſured as diſmal works of darkneſs.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:37387:4"/>
            <div type="exposition">
               <head>AN Enquiry into the Viſion OF THE <hi>Slaying and Riſing</hi> OF THE WITNESSES, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe time of the Propheſying of the Witneſſes being cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, <hi>viz.</hi> 1260 Prophetick days, which are ſo many years; If we can find out the beginning of their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſying, it will diſcover alſo the time of their finiſhing the ſame, and of the Slaying and Riſing of them thereon. But I muſt firſt note a miſtake in Expoſitors in making the 1260 days of their Propheſying, and the Womans abode in the Wilderneſs, to be Synchronal with the 42 Months of the continuance of the Ten-horned-beaſt, and the Treading down of the Outer-Court; whenas the Commencement of the former does precede the latter. Thoſe times being of equal extent does make it eaſy to fall into that miſtake, eſpecially when they cannot much differ in the time of their commencing, but that they differ therein is evident.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> From the continuance of the Ten-horned beaſt after the Witneſſes finiſhing their propheſying. For when they have fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed the ſame, <hi>the beaſt aſcending out of the bottomleſs-pit</hi> (which is the Ten-horned-beaſt) <hi>makes war againſt them and overcomes
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:37387:5"/> them,</hi> &amp;c. Alſo the ſame Beaſt is to continue till the aboliſhing of the Antichriſtian Powers, by the battel of the great day of God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty at the ſeventh Trumpet, and the ſeventh Vial, when the Beaſt and the falſe Prophet are to be caſt into the Lake of Fire. <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.20. Therefore the 42 Months being the ſame extent of time with the 1260 days, and continuing after their Expiring, muſt alſo Commence after them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> From the Perſecution, which the old Serpent being caſt into the Earth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12. did raiſe againſt the Woman fled into the Wilderneſs, before the Riſe of the Ten-horned-beaſt. For after his being ſo caſt down, <hi>he caſts out water like a Flood af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter her to carry her away.</hi> And after he hath ſo ſpent his wrath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her, he proceeds to make war with the Remnant of her Seed, by the Ten-horned-beaſt, <hi>c.</hi> 13. Now the Womans abode in the Wilderneſs being 1260 days (the ſame with the Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſying of the Witneſſes) and there ſuffering this Perſecution pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding to the Riſe of the Ten-horned-beaſt, its plain that the 42 Months of his continuance muſt commence after the 1260 days.</p>
               <p>It appearing therefore, that the 1260 days and 42 Months are not wholly Synchronal, I proceed to the commencement of the firſt, being the time of the Witneſſes Propheſying, and the Womans abode in the Wilderneſs. Thither ſhe fled from the Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Devil, for <hi>her bringing forth the Man-child who was caught up unto Gods Throne, and thereby the Devil caſt out into the Earth.</hi> So that her abode there does commence from the time of his being ſo caſt down; which befell him about the end of <hi>Theodoſius Magnus</hi> his Reign, when the Heathen worſhip became aboliſhed by his ſhutting up the Heathen Temples, and depriving the Prieſts of their Revenues. Whereby the devil fell from his Heavenly Station of being worſhipped as <hi>the God of this World,</hi> as alſo from the Power which upheld that worſhip. Which further appears from the commencement of the Trumpets, which (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> and others) was by the Incurſion of the Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous Nations, which immediately ſucceeded the ſaid <hi>Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> his death. For their ſounding being the ſubject of the ſeventh ſeal, the devils being caſt down muſt immediately precede the ſame being that befell him by the Revolution in the Heathen Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which is the ſubject of the Sixth Seal. His fall from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:37387:5"/> appears therefore, both from the aboliſhing of the Heathen Worſhip, and the immediate ſucceeding of the Trumpets, to be about the end of the ſaid <hi>Theodoſius</hi> his Reign; which Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> makes to end in the year 395, and alſo makes the devils fall from Heaven by the ſaid Revolution in the Sixth Seal, to be then completed or fulfilled.</p>
               <p>But the Perſecution thereon which drives the Woman into the Wilderneſs, having no notable Tranſaction whereto to fix its be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, and being not to be ſuppoſed ſo immediately to ſucceed the devils being caſt out, as not to have ſome ſmall ſpace of time for the raiſing it, and the 1260 days of her abode in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs being a Computation by Centuries with an odd ſixty, its moſt Congruous to make them Commence with the fifth Century which ſo ſoon ſucceeds the ſaid <hi>Theodoſius</hi> his death (<hi>viz.</hi> begins five years after it) and ſo the odd ſixty years to ſucceed a Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tury. And thus making the beginning of the fifth Century to be the <hi>Epocha</hi> of the 1260 days of the Womans abode in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, its clear when they muſt end, <hi>viz.</hi> in the year 1660, and conſequently the 1260 days of the Propheſying of the Witneſſes, which I think none doubt but that its during the ſame time, muſt do the ſame. And as the thus fixing the Epocha of thoſe years or Prophetick days appears ſo reaſonable, ſo the truth thereof will be much confirmed, when we come to apply the ſame to Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory, that is, when we find, that at the end of thoſe days, the ſlaying and riſing of the Witneſſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> became fulfilled, which we find not how otherwaies to make out, ſo as to agree with the Viſion.</p>
               <p>That the time and times and half, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is ſynchronal, or ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies the ſame time with the 1260 days, appears from both being the meaſure of the Womans abode in the Wildernſs, <hi>cap.</hi> 12. But the 42 months of the Ten-horned beaſt cannot commence till the Empire became divided into ten Kingdoms by the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous Nations that over-ran it; which was not till after the middle of the fifth Century. Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> makes it to be ſoon af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the taking <hi>Rome</hi> by <hi>Genſericus</hi> the <hi>Vandal,</hi> which, he ſays, was A.D. 455. <hi>and that the year following or ſoon after, the whole Empire became divided into Ten Kingdoms.</hi> But the reviving of the Ten-horned-beaſt cannot well be reckoned till the expiring of the Weſtern Empire in <hi>Auguſtulus</hi> A.D. 476. For the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors being the ſixth Head, under which the Beaſt received its
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:37387:6"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:37387:6"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:37387:7"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:37387:7"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:37387:8"/> deadly wound by a ſword, that ought to be expired before its reviving under a new Head. Alſo, the Man of Sin was not to be revealed, till, <hi>He that did let (viz.</hi> the ſixth Head or <hi>Roman</hi> Emperors) <hi>was taken out of the way.</hi> And tho' thoſe Emperors, from the taking <hi>Rome</hi> by <hi>Genſericus</hi> to <hi>Auguſtulus,</hi> were ſo incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ble, as to make ſome reckon the Weſtern Empire to end with <hi>Valentinian</hi> the third, yet it did really continue, though in a languiſhing condition, till it expired in <hi>Auguſtulus,</hi> a Name ſuitable to the ſtate it was then dwindled into. And whenas its expiring is deſcribed in the third Trumpet, by a <hi>great ſtar falling from Heaven, its Name being called Worm-wood,</hi> the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable condition of the Empire under thoſe petty Emperors, and their perplext troubles do beſt ſuit with that Character. And the not reviving of the Ten-horned-beaſt till then, does well enough agree with the ten Horns, or <hi>ten Kings receiving Power as Kings one hour with the Beaſt;</hi> for that ſignifies no more than that they received ſuch Power about the ſame time with the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viving of the Beaſt. And by the latitude of Mr. <hi>Medes</hi>'s words before cited, it might be very nigh the ſaid expiring of the Weſtern Empire, before the Empire became divided into ten Kingdoms.</p>
               <p>And as the not reviving of the Ten-horned-beaſt till the ſaid A.D. 476 does ſo well agree with thoſe Kings receiving Power as Kings one hour with the Beaſt, ſo it better ſuits with the Power and Corruptions of Antichriſt being then more advanced, to ſit him for reviving and heading the Ten-horned-beaſt. And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as he is repreſented by a Two-horned-beaſt, ſignifying the two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold Power he claims, <hi>viz.</hi> Eccleſiaſtical and Civil, anſwering to his Authority of Prieſt and King, whoſe Vice-gerent he aſſumes to be, (and therefore he is ſaid to wear the Horns of the Lamb) he begins to head the Ten-horned-beaſt, by exerciſing onely the firſt of theſe Powers, till by his Pſeudo-prophetick deceits, he hath ſo advanced himſelf and deluded the World, as to make way for his claiming the other Power alſo. In the mean time ſteps in the other King, who was to continue but a ſhort ſpace, and was no <hi>Roman</hi> but a Foreign Head. And this was <hi>Odoacer</hi> King of the <hi>Herculi</hi> with the ſucceeding <hi>Oſtrogoths.</hi> So that, <hi>Odo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acer</hi> extinguiſhing the Weſtern Empire, by vanquiſhing <hi>Auguſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> the eighth Head, which is the ſeventh <hi>Roman</hi>-head, does, as to one of his Powers which he exerciſeth, begin to head the Beaſt
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:37387:8"/> at the ſame time with the riſe of the foreign Head, which was to continue but a ſhort ſpace, <hi>viz.</hi> both at the expiring of the ſixth Head, the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperors. But he is not reputed the eighth Head till his exerciſing the other Power alſo. The firſt Power fulfils the revealing of the Man of Sin at the expiring of the ſixth Head, and the other being civil, makes him agree with the other Heads, and ſo become <hi>the eighth Head which one of the ſeven,</hi> or the ſeventh <hi>Roman</hi> Head.</p>
               <p>My making the Commencement of the 1260 days to precede the 42 months, is further made good out of <hi>Daniel.</hi> For it's ſaid of the little Horn there, <hi>cap.</hi> 7. which is the Antichriſtian-head of the Ten-horned-beaſt, <hi>That the Saints of the Moſt High ſhall be given into his hands, for a Time and Times, and the dividing of a Time, and then Judgment ſhall ſit to take away his dominion, and to conſume it unto the end.</hi> Now the ſaid time and times, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> being the ſame as before ſhewed, with the 1260 days, and at the end thereof Judgment beginning to ſit to take away the dominion of the ſaid Horn, or Ten-horned-beaſt under that Head, he is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to continue after the 1260 days till his dominion be taken away and conſumed, which how long it is, ſeems concludible from <hi>Daniel, cap.</hi> 12. Where we find again the ſaid time and times and half, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> during which, <hi>the ſcattering of the power of the Holy People ſhould be,</hi> (which is the ſame with the ſaid giving the Saints into the hands of the ſaid Beaſt) and then on <hi>Daniel</hi>'s enquiring, <hi>What ſhall be the end of thoſe Wonders</hi> there ſpoken of? He is denyed an Anſwer, as enquiring into things, <hi>that are cloſed and ſealed up till the time of the end;</hi> yet is told of two pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riods of time which will make great diſcovery of what he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires after, <hi>viz. From the taking away the daily ſacrifice, and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up the Abomination that maketh deſolate, there ſhall be</hi> 1290 <hi>days: Bleſſed is he that waiteth and cometh to the</hi> 1335 <hi>days.</hi> Which Numbers, tho' they reſpect the Profanation of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple by <hi>Antiochus Epiphanes,</hi> yet as he is generally agreed to be a Type of Antichriſt, ſo they in a Typical ſenſe reſpect his Reign, and ſo muſt have the ſame Epocha with the preceding time and times, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> there, which they relate to. And then the time and times, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or 1260 days ending, as before ſhewed, in the year 1660, the 1290 days muſt end in 1690, and the 1335 days in 1735. So that, whereas at the expiring of time and times, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or 1260 days, Judgment begins to ſit to take away the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:37387:9"/> dominion of the Beaſt (on the riſing of the Witneſſes after the ſlaying them at the end of thoſe days) the 1290 days denote a time, the year 1690, at which ſome very remarkable advance will be made therein, or ſome notable Tranſactions or Revolutions will fall out in order thereunto. But the 1335 days denote a time, the year 1735, at which the taking away his dominion or deſtroying him will be ſo completed, as to make them Bleſſed or peculiarly happy that reach thereunto.</p>
               <p>Now as to the falling out of ſuch an event in the year 1690, as I have ſpoken of, we have ſeen what great Tranſactions and Changes, of ſuch tendency, both at home and abroad, that with the preceding and following year hath produced, and what fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we are in continual expectation of. And as to the event to fall out in the year 1735, I take it to be the ſounding of the ſeventh Trumpet. For on the ſlaying and riſing of the Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and their aſcending in a Cloud, and the falling thereon of the Tenth Part of the City, it's ſaid, <hi>The ſecond Woe is paſt and the third Woe cometh quickly.</hi> Which Fall of the Tenth Part of the City, (of which after) I take to be a chief part of the event ſignified to fall out or commence in the year 1690. And we ſee how the ſtate of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Empire, the ſecond Woe-Trumpet, does agree with the ſeventh Trumpet its being the other event. Which hath received ſuch a deadly Wound, as to make it <note n="‖" place="margin">Which is fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the time for which the <hi>Euphratean</hi> Horſe-men or Turks, are looſed, <hi>Re.</hi> 9.5. to execute the ſecond Woe-Trumpet on the Empire: For the <hi>Day, Month &amp; Year,</hi> being Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Days, make 396 years, the Epo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cha of which, being about the beginning of the Four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tury, when the Turks began their Eruption from <hi>Euphrates</hi> on the Empire, they muſt be now near expiring, and therewith end that Trumpet, or the Empire that inflicted that Plague. At leaſt ſo far as to make it ceaſe from continuing the Plague of a Woe-Trumpet; but the abſolute breaking of that Empire, ſeems not to be till the ſixth Vial, and then it will fulfil <hi>The drying up the River</hi> Euphrates <hi>to make way for the Kings of the</hi> Eaſt.</note> unlikely to laſt long, and at preſent even to ceaſe from continuing the Plague of a Woe-Trumpet. And being at the time when the ſecond Woe-Trumpet is paſt, and the tenth part of the City is fallen, (both which are now about being fulfilled) it's ſaid, <hi>The third Woe cometh quickly,</hi> it can hardly be at a greater diſtance than the ſaid year 1735; and therefore the great event ſignified then to fall out, muſt in all likelihood be it. Which is much confirmed by the 42 months of the continuance of the Beaſt ſo agreeing therewith. For his time beginning in the year 476, and ending at the ſeventh Trumpet, as before ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the 42 months from the ſaid Epocha end in the year 1736 the year after the ſaid 1735.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:37387:9"/>
               <p>But it may be objected, That the ſaid Numbers of <hi>Daniel,</hi> in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e typical ſenſe mentioned, ſhould rather commence with the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> months of the Antichriſtian Reign, which in their typical ſenſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ey reſpect, than with the 1260 days which have an higher E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ha. To which I ſay, that <hi>the taking away the dayly Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> &amp;c. may in a typical ſenſe, be well applyed to the Epocha <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the 1260 days, both in reſpect of the perſecution by which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Devil cauſed the Woman to fly into the Wilderneſs, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>o in reſpect of the Advance Antichriſt had then made in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ing the World with the Myſteries of Iniquity. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e, though his Reign cannot be ſaid to commence till he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e a new Head of the Ten-horned-beaſt, ſucceeding the ſixth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ead which expired A.D. 476. yet thoſe Numbers, in their ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>al ſenſe, may well reſpect him before the proper commence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>nt of his Reign. And they being there introduced in reference <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the preceding time and times, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as aforeſaid, they are to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ve the ſame Epocha, and ſo notifie ſignal times of the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>g and accompliſhing the deliverance of the People of God, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ch commenceth at the end of time and times, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or 1260 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ys, by the riſing of the Witneſſes after the ſlaying them, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Judgment that then begins to ſit, as aforeſaid, to take <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ay the dominion of the Beaſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Having thus diſcovered the time of the expiring of the 1260 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ys, and ſo of the ſlaying and riſing of the Witneſſes thereon, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e are next to enquire, How Hiſtory Anſwers the ſame, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ere and how the ſame hath been fulfilled? The year 1660, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ing, as before ſhewed, the time of the expiring of the 1260 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ys, nothing then fell out that appears capable of Anſwering <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e deſcription of the ſlaying and riſing of the Witneſſes, unleſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> great Revolution by the Reſtauration. The ſlaying them is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ed chiefly to one of the ten Kingdoms the Empire was divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>d into, by the falling of the Tenth Part of the City (that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> one of thoſe ten Kingdoms) on their riſing and aſcending <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Cloud. And what Kingdom can this be but <hi>ENGLAND?</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>deed the <hi>French</hi> Perſecution, and alſo the <hi>Hungarian</hi> did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> about the ſame time, both the <hi>French</hi> and the Imperial Court <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ing Encouragement thereunto from our KING's Reſtaura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>n (as well they might, conſidering what he as well as his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>er proved to be) on which, and the preceding <hi>Pyrenean</hi> Peace, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Deſign was ſet on foot for Ruining the Reformed Religion.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:37387:10"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:37387:10"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:37387:11"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:37387:11"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:37387:12"/> So that it's a very remarkable time for the ſlaying of the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes to commence at, which conſidered, together with the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I have given for the 1260 days ending then, ſeems to make it unqueſtionable to be the true time thereof. But nothing then or ſince fell out in <hi>France</hi> or elſewhere but in <hi>England,</hi> that can anſwer the Viſion of the ſlaying them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For it's ſaid thereon, <hi>They that dwell on the Earth ſhall rejoyce and make merry, and ſend Giſts one to another, becauſe that thoſe two Prophets tormented them that dwell on the Earth.</hi> But no ſuch rejoycing hath been at thoſe foreign Perſecutions, they being not ſo much approved of as to cauſe ſuch ſolemn rejoycings, but on the contrary, thoſe that have been deeply concerned in promoting the <hi>French</hi> Perſecution, have been aſhamed to own the ſame; it being ſo inhumane and barbarous as to move pity and favour from Papiſts themſelves; whereas it's well known, what great and ſolemn rejoycings there was both at home and abroad, for the King's Reſtauration, by reaſon that the dwellers on earth had been tormented by that Party which was then prevailed againſt, and which thereon was retaliated with thoſe ſevere puniſhments and ſufferings, which they have ſince undergone.</p>
               <p>But then, How was the Witneſſes, lying dead three days and a half, (that is three years and a half) fulfilled in <hi>England?</hi> To which I ſay, That there may be ſuch a ſymbolical meaning of their lying dead, as to make the fulfilling thereof according to the Prophetick time needleſs. For it may refer to <hi>Antiochu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Epiphanes</hi> his Prophaning the Temple, and to the time of <hi>Ely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah</hi>'s mournful propheſying, when he cauſed great Famine by ſhut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up Heaven, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (both which were for the ſame time) and ſo ſigniſie, that their lying dead ſhall be alike ſhort time of Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, and have th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> like happy Iſſue. Yet, a fulfilling thereof ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the prophetick time may be aptly enough aſſigned. For reckoning the ſlaying the Witneſſes here, chiefly to reſpec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the excluding ſo many Non-conforming Miniſters by the <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholomew</hi>-Act (yet including alſo thoſe who were ſhut out of Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Employment by the Corporation-Act, or otherwaies, for fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring that Cauſe that was then ſo run down) from <hi>Bartholo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mew</hi>-day 1662, the three years and half will end in <hi>Februar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 1665. About which time the dreadful Plague had ſo finiſhe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> its ſlaughter, as to make the Citizens flock faſt to <hi>London</hi> agai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And the Non conforming Miniſters, having, during the Plague,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:37387:12"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Riſque of that danger which the Pariſh-Miniſters ſled <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and ſupplyed their Pulpits which they deſerted, did there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> gain that Reputation with the City, as was a beginning of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e <hi>Entrance of the ſpirit of Life into them to ſet them on their</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. For the People were ſo affected with that dreadful Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ent, and the Zeal and Faithfulneſs to their Duty which the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on-conforming Miniſters did manifeſt thereon, as much to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ntenance their Meetings which they were then encouraged <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſet up, and were ſo born out therein, that the <hi>Oxford</hi>-Act <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>de during the Plague, could take little effect to drive them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>om the City. On which ſee Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Non-conformiſts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ea for Peace, <hi>p.</hi> 236, 237, 238, 239. and he hath theſe remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>le Words thereon, <hi>[Thus the dreadful Plague, began that which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſo much offendeth as a dangerous Schiſm.]</hi> Alſo the next diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>l Judgment which laid the City in Aſhes, (and ſo gave more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>untenance to the Non-conformiſts Meetings, by reaſon of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>iſh-Churches being deſtroyed) and the Unſucceſsfulneſs of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e <hi>Dutch</hi> War (wherewith it was expected to ruine that Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>) were, together with the preceding Plague, ſuch aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>g Providences, as muſt needs ſtrike the evil World with ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ead of that Divine Power, ſo wonderfully manifeſted in its <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>dgments. But the Contemplation thereof was ſuch reviving <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>d animating of the Witneſſes, (which might be with a due <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>paſſion of the evils inſlicted by thoſe Judgments) and an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ancing of their Repute and Intereſt, as to complete the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>g them on their feet from their ſlain condition.</p>
               <p>Which begat in their Adverſaries ſuch fear of them, (fulfill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>g what is ſaid of the Witneſſes raiſed again on their feet, <hi>That <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>t fear fell on them that ſaw them</hi>) as brought the Penal Laws <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> them to ſuppreſs, and hath ſince begotten many politick Arts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> keep them under, and hinder their aſcending in a Cloud to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Heaven of Power, whether the great Voice, <hi>ver.</hi> 12. does <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> them. Notwithſtanding which they have continued ſtill e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ging in the World, and will do ſo till that Voice be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ed. And as our late Revolution hath gained them that Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ty, which is like to be ſo holding as to prove <hi>an open Door <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>em which no man can ſhut,</hi> ſo it ſeems deſigned alſo for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>illing that Voice, and thereby accompliſhing the Fall of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>th Part of the City, though the ſame be hitherto much ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>cted, by continuance ſtill of the former Enmity againſt them,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:37387:13"/> and Jealouſies of them, notwithſtanding the great detriment the Publick receives thereby. Though this Viſion thus concerns our Nation, as it chiefly reſpects one of the ten Kingdoms the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire was divided into, (as before noted) yet it hath alſo a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>current fulfilling in other Countries, where the afore mentioned deſign againſt the Reformed Religion, on the Reſtauration, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> hath been purſued to the utmoſt; whereby, as the ſlaying of the Witneſles hath been fulfilled with them, ſo there hath and will be a fulfilling of their Reſurrection, by the aforeſaid Judgment that now ſits, at the end of time and times, <hi>&amp;c. To take away the dominion of the Beaſt, and to conſume it unto the end.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Account of the ſlaying and riſing of the Witneſſes, as reſpecting one of the ten Kingdoms, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is further confirmed from the Perſecution here which ſucceeded the Reſtauration, its better agreeing with the ſlaying of the Witneſſes, than thoſe Perſecutions which then and ſince have faln out elſewhere, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhort of their barbarous Inhumanity, though ſo ſevere and heavy as to prove ruinous to many; and ſo, better anſwering to the ſlaying the Witneſſes, which is different from the former Antichriſtian Perſecutions, both as being peculiar to the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes (the Worſhippers in the Inner-Court or Temple and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar) whereas the former extends alſo to the Outer-Court trod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den down, and as being not ſo much deſigned to deſtroy, as to ſilence and ſubdue; importing a political and a ſpiritual Death, (<hi>viz.</hi> as to their exerciſing their Function of Propheſying) from whence they are raiſed by the <hi>Spirit of LIFE entring into them, &amp;c.</hi> Alſo the Perſecution here is more likely than any elſewhere to be the ſlaying the Witneſſes, becauſe the Sufferers under it were ſuch as eſpouſed the Cauſe they were engaged in upon their own Judgment and Choice, and much contrary to their worldly Intereſt, both in reſpect of their excluding them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves thereby from Preferments, and alſo expoſing themſelves to manifold evils, from Puniſhment of Laws, and Enmity of their prevailing Adverſaries. Whereas the Perſecution in <hi>France</hi> and elſewhere, being againſt a Religion ſo long eſtabliſhed by Law, that the Profeſſors of it received it by Education, it was there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore like a National Religion which involves all Profeſſors true or falſe, and ſo had multitudes in its Communion, not ſo much from Principles of Conſcience, as the Influence of Education, whereby the Truth was not ſo rooted in their hearts, as to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:37387:13"/> enable them to abide thoſe Tryals that came upon them.</p>
               <p>But this Account of the ſlaying and riſing of the Witneſſes, tho' enforced with ſo ſtrong Reaſons, will not be eaſily digeſted by thoſe who ſo highly eſteem the Reformation, as to make the breaking then with <hi>Rome,</hi> to be a diſmembring us from the Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horned-beaſt, or a ſeparating this Kingdom from continuing one of the Horns thereof. Which cannot be, if the ſlaying the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes was fulfilled according to my Account thereof. For they being <hi>ſlain by the Beaſt that aſcends out of the Bottomleſs-pit,</hi> (that is the Ten-horned-beaſt, which <hi>cap.</hi> 13. is ſaid to ariſe out of the Sea, and <hi>cap.</hi> 17. to aſcend out of the Bottomleſs-pit) this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom muſt continue a Member of that Beaſt, or one of the Horns thereof at the time of the ſlaying them. Which that it did ſo, ſeems ſo clear from other Reaſons alſo, as to make it hardly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivable to be otherwaies. For the Reformation made no Alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in the Civil Government, and therefore could not make any as to this Kingdoms continuing a Part or Member of the Ten-horned-beaſt, which is a repreſentation of the Politick or Civil State of the Empire. Nor did it make any in the Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Juriſdiction (ſo called) the ſame Hierarchy continuing here, with rejection of the foreign Juriſdiction uſurpt by the Pope. And though the Reformation made in Religion was much Praiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy, as a good beginning, yet it fell much ſhort of obeying that Voice, <hi>Come out of her my People,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Rev.</hi> 18. And yet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of making further progreſs it proved retrograde, and back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſliding, became ſo prevalent, as to beget diſmal apprehenſions of our relapſing to what we had reformed from, and thereby in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volved us in the calamities of the Civil War. Yet ſo far were we from being warned thereby, that the Reſtauration proved a reviving of the ſame deſigns which before had produced ſuch ſad effects, and which now became more eagerly driven on, both out of enmity to that Party which were God's Scourge for the former purſuing the ſame, and alſo to prevent the like ſufferings from them again, by a total ſuppreſſing them.</p>
               <p>It appears therefore, that the Antichriſtian Spirit of the World hath been the prevailing or predominant Spirit in the Nation ſince the Reformation, and how can it then not continue us of the ſame Antichriſtian-body (the Ten-horned-beaſt) as former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, whatever Variance we have had ſince with <hi>Rome?</hi> And being refin'd in Profeſſion by the Reformation, whilſt the ſame Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:37387:14"/> Spirit and worldly Power continues to bear ſway, does rather make us more complete Members of that Beaſt, than make us ceaſe from continuing Members thereof, the Myſtery of Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity conſiſting in warring againſt Chriſt under a Chriſtian Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, or <hi>having Horns like a Lamb, yet ſpeaking as a Dragon.</hi> And ſuch Reformation in ſuch enlightened times, is indeed ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable for the prolonging of worldly Power in oppoſition to the coming of Chriſts Kingdom, whilſt <hi>Satan being transformed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an Angel of Light, and his Miniſters into Miniſters of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs,</hi> become thereby enabled the longer to vye with the true Children of Light. Alſo the 1260 days of the Witneſſes Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſying and the Womans abode in the Wilderneſs ending, as before ſhewed, but in the year 1660, (and by ſome not ſo ſoon) the Reformation could make no Viſible Chriſtian Church, whilſt the Woman (the true Church) continues ſo long after in her ſecret hid condition from the face of the Serpent. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, the National Church ſince the Reformation, continuing a politick Body as before, the Ligament of whoſe Union being humane Laws ſupported by worldly Power, and thereby com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending all but thoſe who ſeparate from her for Conſcience ſake, even the moſt wicked hypocritical Profeſſors as well as true Chriſtians (like Tares and Wheat growing together) how can this Church (ſo called) pretend to be a real Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Church, or Member of the Church of Chriſt which is his Body? The Union of which is by that Spiritual Ligament, which knits each Member to other, and the whole to Chriſt its Head, whence it hath Nouriſhment miniſtred for its Spiritual growth and edifying. So that, it ſeems evident, that the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation could make no ſuch Change, as to make the Nation ceaſe from continuing a worldly Politick-body, and Member of the Apocalyptick-beaſt as before.</p>
               <p>The ſlaying the Witneſſes proving therefore fulfilled by the ſaid Reſtauration, it muſt moderate the ſevere Cenſures which that Party that was then prevailed againſt hath been ſince black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with. Their Actions in the late times did ſo tranſcend the meaſures of human worldly Affairs, as muſt needs make them ſeem very unaccountable to thoſe who can judge of them only by their outer appearance, and ſo may well incur ſevere Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures from them. But thoſe, who, by the Light of Prophecies, can contemplate the tranſactions of thoſe times, as an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:37387:14"/> work of Providence for the advancing of Chriſt's King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and quelling all oppoſition to it, muſt ſurely judge other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies. That War may well be reckon'd the Concluſion of the third Vial. That Vial contains thoſe many bloody wars which ſucceeded the Reformation (which was the ſecond Vial) and were occaſioned by it, <hi>viz.</hi> that between us and the <hi>Spaniards</hi> on their Invaſion, and that between them and the <hi>Dutch</hi> on their Revolt, and the <hi>Hugonet</hi> Wars in <hi>France,</hi> and the long diſmal <hi>German</hi> War, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ended with our Civil War. After which the Treaty at <hi>Munſter</hi> in the year 1648, concluded that bloody Vial, by the Peace it gave to Chriſtendom. And that year proved ſo diſaſtrous to Crowned Heads, as makes it remarkable for commencing the fourth Vial poured on the Sun, as well as for ending the third Vial. The moſt ſignal inſtance whereof, was the hard Fate that befel <hi>CHARLES</hi> the Firſt. Who being ſwayed to ſuch Exceſſes in Government as were perillous and Ruinous to True Religion, and the Rights and Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of the Subject, and therein obſtructive to the Advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Chriſt's Kingdom, it brought the ſame Plague of the third Vial on this Nation, which had befallen other Nations for the like doings. Wherein his own part of ſuffering ſeems ſevere, after he had yielded ſo far in giving ſatisfaction for that Male-Adminiſtration of Government which he had been ſeduced into. But his Conceſſions were with ſuch Reſerve, as did not yield ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity from the like Evils befalling the Nation again; or however, would not comport with the Progreſs that was then to be made in furthering the coming of Chriſt's Kingdom, by finiſhing the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſying of the Witneſſes, in order to their ſlaying and riſing again, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and therefore the Zealots for promoting the Intereſt of that Kingdom, could ſind no ſatisfaction in ſuch conceſſions, how plauſible and ſatisfactory ſoever they appeared to others to be; and thereon preſumed, in a tranſcendent Inſtance, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Miniſters of the wrath of God declared againſt all world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Power that does not ſubmit to the Sceptre of Chriſt Jeſus. But their Zeal herein exceeding their Acting according the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Judgments of Truth, they failed of becoming eſtabliſhed in their ſucceſs, and were ſo prevailed againſt by their Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, as to receive from them the ſame meaſure which they had meted. Yet this does not exclude their being ſuch Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of God as I have mentioned, and they approved themſelves
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:37387:15"/> to be ſuch who underwent the utmoſt Tryal of Sufferings, dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as men at peace with God, and not condemned of him tho' judged of man. And its ſome exeuſe for them, that they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to have been influenced by the Jeſuites in that great Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action, [ſee Dr. <hi>du Moulin</hi>'s Vindication of the Proteſt. Relig. <hi>&amp;c. pag.</hi> 59.] whoſe ſubtle Inſtigations found their Zeal a ſit Subject to work on. And the proſperity of that Cauſe was ſuch till it had finiſhed its Courſe, as muſt ſurely make God's own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and eſpouſing the ſame diſcernable to all, unleſs ſuch, as <hi>when his hand is lifted up will not ſee.</hi> And the Adherents to it had the priviledge, by their proſperous ſucceſs, to finiſh the mournful Propheſying of the Witneſſes in this Nation, and then by their being ſo prevailed againſt, to accompliſh the ſlaying them, in order to their riſing again, and aſcending to a triumphant ſtate over their former ſufferings. Which we ſee now in a good meaſure fulfilled, and are like to ſee the Accompliſhing thereof, by the fall of the tenth part of the City, which ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds the riſing of the Witneſſes, and their aſcending in a Cloud, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And what is meant by that Fall is our next Enquiry, ſo far as we can ſearch into what is not yet fulfilled. It plainly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports ſuch a Change as will make the Nation ceaſe from con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing a Part or Member of the Ten-horned-beaſt, which, as appears, it did not by the Reformation, and that ſince (ſave the Interruption by the Civil War) we have been rather back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſliding, than making further progreſs out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> till our late Revolution, which hath freed us from ſuch danger of relapſing, and ſeems deſigned to complete our coming out from thence, (though we hitherto make but ſlow Progreſs therein) by ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhing the fall of the tenth part of the City. By which ſeems to be meant, the expiring of all the Power which the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil gave to the Ten-horned beaſt, <hi>cap.</hi> 13. wherewith <hi>To war with the Saints and overcome them;</hi> which, however it be diminiſhed, ſo continues as to hinder the Witneſſes Aſcent to that ſtation, whether the <hi>Great Voice</hi> does call them, that is, to exclude them from ſuch employment in the Government, as would moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce to God's Glory and the Weal-publick, and ſo promote the Intereſt of Chriſt's Kingdom in the Nation. And whilſt the Enmity againſt them does ſo continue, as thus to ſuppreſs them and keep them under, and thereby to obſtruct the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:37387:15"/> of Chriſt's Kingdom, its a continuing of the ſaid War againſt the Saints, and ſo makes the Nation not yet ceaſe from continuing one of the Horns of the Ten horned-beaſt. So that, till <hi>the Judgment that now ſits to take away the dominion of the Beaſt,</hi> hath ſo prevailed againſt all ſuch Antichriſtian Power, as to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the Government, as to the exerciſing thereof, to a like im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent State with thoſe Beaſts, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.12. <hi>Whoſe dominion is taken away though their Lives be prolonged,</hi> the fall of the tenth part of the City ſeems not accompliſhed.</p>
               <p>But there's reaſon to reckon the fulfilling thereof near, both from the light of this Viſion, and alſo from our ſeeing that Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer ſo declining and languiſhing, that all politick bands, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle workings of the deceiver for upholding and prolonging it, prove like <hi>the looſed tacklings that cannot ſtrengthen their Maſts, nor ſpread their Sails,</hi> whereby the Nation, as to the worldly poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick ſtate of it, is in alike unhing'd, and crazy tottering condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as in <hi>Eſay</hi> 24.19,20. is deſcribed to precede the glorious ſtate of Chriſt's Kingdom. And the Conflict that does ſpring from this declenſion of worldly Power, and the emerging of the Witneſſes aſcending in a Cloud, is the cauſe of our preſent Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and Diſtractions. Nor can we well hope for ſettlement and proſperity, till the Judgment that ſits hath ended this Conflict, by ſo taking away the dominion or power of the Beaſt, as to fulfil the Fall of the tenth part of the City, and the great Voice that calls the Witneſſes up to Heaven. This will give new Life and Vigour to the Government, <hi>By the Lord being exalted among us to fill us with Judgment and Righteouſneſs, and make wiſdom and knowledge the ſtability of our Times, and ſtrength of Salvation.</hi> It will be a laying the Foundation of <hi>that City whoſe Builder and Maker is God,</hi> whereby we ſhall find Him carrying on that Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Building, till he hath raiſed us up to the glorious ſtate of the New <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> And it will be ſuch a preludious commenc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Chriſt's Kingdom in the Nation, as will occaſion great Changes throughout Chriſtendom; and ſo be a preparative mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing way for the great Revolution at the ſeventh Trumpet, which ſettles Him in his Kingdom on Earth; and therein be a great tranſaction of the fifth Vial, <hi>which fils the Kingdom of the Beaſt with darkneſs.</hi> And indeed, that Vial ſeems to commence from our late great Revolution; and ſo the <hi>Exit</hi> of King <hi>James</hi> did conclude the fourth Vial poured on the Sun, as we have before
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:37387:16"/> noted his Fathers Fate to be a ſignal Tranſaction of its begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. But then, whereas the preſent Conſederacy againſt <hi>France</hi> is the reſult of that Revolution, which ſeems not well eſtabliſhed till the Confederates have ſo ſucceeded againſt that Sun, which hath ſhined with much ſcorching heat to the great annoyance of Chriſtendom, as to make him ſet in a Cloud; when this befals him, (which ſeems very hopeful as well as deſireable) it may well be reckoned a Tranſaction belonging to the fourth Vial, as being ſo connext with King <hi>James</hi>'s <hi>Exit,</hi> that the Fall of the one did involve the others Fall.</p>
               <p>Since therefore ſo great Conſequences are like to attend our late Revolution, they are much in the dark, who are ſo much concerned for our ſettling upon our old bottom or worldly ſtate, acquieſcing in the Deliverance received, as if it rendred us as happy as is to be deſired, or however to be expected; like thoſe who reject all ſpeculations of Chriſt's Kingdom on Earth, tell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us, that he came not to intereſt himſelf in, or give diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance to the Rights of Princes or Civil Governments, <hi>his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom being not of this world,</hi> ſhewing themſelves of like ſpirit with thoſe who ſaid, <hi>We will not have this Man reign over us.</hi> But tho' his Kingdom be from above, as He himſelf was, and not from beneath, of this world, or according to the courſe thereof, yet its in this world, where <hi>He must reign till he hath put down all Authority and Power, all Enemies under his feet,</hi> and ſo make <hi>the Kingdoms of the World become the Kingdoms of our Lord and his Chriſt,</hi> &amp;c. And the Laws and Liberties which we ſo Joy in, are owing to the advancement of his Kingdom on Earth. But the world being unable ſo to conſider them, claims them as the Rights of Free-born People, and which our Rulers are bound to obſerve by Original Contract with the People, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Whenas indeed, what Change there is in the Government of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian world, from the abſolute dominion of Heathen Princes, proceeds from the Victory gained over the powers of the world, by the Man-child being caught up unto God's Throne to rule, and the Dragon being caſt out into the Earth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12. which cauſed the great Revolution in the Empire deſcribed in the ſixth Seal.</p>
               <p>And what Liberty or Freedom can any pretend to, who are <hi>the Servants of Sin and Satan, who having the Power of Death, through fear of it, makes them all their Liver-time ſubject to Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage.</hi>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:37387:16"/> Which Bondage of Corruption all Mankind are ſubject to, ſo far as Redemption, through Chriſt Jeſus hath not freed them from it. And they being thus the Children of wrath, under the Thraldom of the <hi>Prince of the power of the Air, the ſpirit that worketh in the Children of Diſobedience,</hi> what Rights or Priviledges could they obtain? Or what Aſſurance could they have of them when granted, by abſolute Heathen Rulers under the Prince of darkneſs? Whoſe Power did ſet them above the need of making ſuch Grants, and could eaſily fruſtrate them when made. So that, the Grants and Conceſſions whereby the Princes of Chriſtendom have obliged themſelves to their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and thereby enfranchiſed them from Heathen Thraldom, are owing to the downfal of the Devils power by his being caſt out of Heaven, whereby they being unable to continue that ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute dominion, were driven to comply with their Subjects by ſuch Conceſſions. And though his power hath been ſo reſtored by the Impoſtures of the falſe Prophet, and other his ſubtle Arts to corrupt the Nations of Chriſtendom, as in ſome Countries almoſt to fruſtrate the benefit of that Victory over him, yet in others it continues to be enjoyed, and with that firmneſs in our Country, as to make both former and latter Attempts to deprive us of it fatal to the Undertakers. And the late Revolution ſeems not onely deſign'd to confirm to us that Benefit when there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared ſo much danger of loſing it, but alſo much to enlarge the ſame, by that advancemene of Chriſt's Kingdom, which is ſignified by the Fall of the tenth part of the City.</p>
               <p>But we ſeem inſenſible thereof, and as little diſpoſed to, and prepared for ſo great a Bleſſing, as <hi>Lot</hi> and his Family were to depart out of <hi>Sodom,</hi> to eſcape deſtruction. It's too high a Bleſſing for the world to like, tho' it be well pleaſed with than already received, of being freed from Heathen Thraldom. It can like ſuch Bleſſings that free it from the evils and miſeries that attend its lapſed ſtate, <hi>lying in wickedneſs,</hi> but is not pleaſed with ſuch Bleſſings that tend to recover it out of that ſtate by Reforming its Corruptions. Which Indiſpoſition to higher Bleſſings deſigned us, makes the world ſo little ſenſible to whom to aſcribe what we already enjoy, and ſo to fail of rendring Him due Praiſe and Thanks for the ſame, <hi>to whom all Judgment is committed, that all men ſhould honour the Son as they honour the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> Men of the world can gladly embrace Chriſt as a Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:37387:17"/> to reconcile them to God, and ſo to become their Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our in the next world, and as ſuch do him much Honour, yet they cannot like of his being their King to Rule and Govern them in this world, and therefore little own him as ſuch; tho' ſurely they cannot well hope to find him the one to them who are averſe to his being the other.</p>
               <p>But whatever oppoſition the coming of his Kingdom does meet with from the Enmity of the world, yet <hi>God will ſet his King upon his holy Hill of</hi> Sion, <hi>and out of</hi> Sion <hi>will ſend forth the Rod of his ſtrength to make him rule in the midst of his Enemies.</hi> But He can have no Enemies, but thoſe who are ſo to Truth and Righteouſneſs, the bringing of which on Earth is the end of his Kingdom, whereunto <hi>He will conſume the Man of Sin with the breath of his mouth, and deſtroy him with the brightneſs of his coming.</hi> Which hath already ſo enlightened the world, as to make great diſcovery of, and thereby much to advance the deſtruction of that <hi>Son of Perdition;</hi> &amp; which will further ſo enlighten it, as to diſperſe all the Clouds of darkneſs wherewith the Deceiver hath overwhelmed the deluded world, <hi>destroy the face of covering cast over all People, and the vail ſpread over all Nations,</hi> whereby the Holy Mountain on which the Lord ſitteth King, <hi>ſhall be esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in the Top of the Mountains, and be exalted above the Hills, and all Nations ſhall flow unto it, and ſo the Moon ſhall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded and the Sun aſhamed, when the Lord of Hoſts ſhall reign in</hi> Mount Sion <hi>and in</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>and before his Antients glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ſly.</hi> The accompliſhing whereof is now haſtening, by the Judgment that ſits to take away the dominion of the Beaſt, on the Witneſſes being riſen; and to bleſs us with a preludious fulfilling thereof by the Fall of the tenth part of the City, ſeems to be the preſent work of Providence in this Nation.</p>
               <p>To make us ſenſible whereof, and thereby to prepare us for complyance therewith, and furtherance thereof, ſeems to be the meaning of the great Change of Affairs that ſucceeded our late wonderful proſperous Revolution, <hi>viz.</hi> of the great Troubles that have ſince exerciſed and perplext us, and brought us into great danger of confuſion and ruine. Wherein God's diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure with us is evident, yet accompanyed with ſignal Inſtances of his good Providence over us, which ſhew the evils that have befaln us, not to be the Judgments of his Wrath, but admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing Chaſtiſements, <hi>Whom I love I rebuke and chaſten, be zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:37387:17"/> therefore and repent.</hi> And we ſhall not be at a loſs to find out the Cauſe of his Diſpleaſure, if we conſider how the croſs Influence of carnal Intereſt and worldly Wiſdom, does obſtruct the improving our late great Deliverance to its deſigned end; as if we were as afraid of advancing further in Reformation, as we were lately of backſliding into Popery; but were minded to fix in a luke-warm <hi>Laodicean</hi>-ſtate, flattering our ſelves with that Church, till we incur the Judgment threatned to her. Of God's diſpleaſure at ſuch unrighteous doings we have felt the effects, and are like further to do ſo, till we become inſtructed thereby, to improve the great Bleſſing received to a furthering that greater deſigned us; whereby, ſo to raiſe up in us the love of Truth and power of Godlineſs, as to make all ſiniſter Counſels of world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Wiſdom, and all lifeleſs Formalities of Phariſaical Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs to vaniſh, and the Worſhipping God in Spirit and in Truth, and the ſerving Him in righteouſneſs and holineſs, to become the prevailing Spirit in the Nation, and ſo to influence all adminiſtration of Affairs for the moſt advantagious promoting the ſame. And as there's ſo little proſpect of our becoming otherwaies ſettled, ſo the various wonderful Providences, which in this Age have befallen this Nation, have in a good meaſure prepared us for ſuch a Change, <hi>When thy Judgments are in the Earth, the Inhabitants of the World will learn Righteouſneſs;</hi> tho' the ſame be much obſcured by the ſpirit of the World conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing yet predominant, but will be manifeſt, when the end of thoſe Providences become diſcovered, by their iſſuing in that happy Change which will transform us into a true Chriſtian Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, and ſo, make us <hi>Rejoyce with the joy of Gods People, and glory with his Inheritance,</hi> being freed from <hi>Other Lords beſides Him having Dominion over us;</hi> that is, from the Thraldom of Worldly Power, or the Spirit of the World continuing predo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minant.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The great Earthquake at the ſame hour,</hi> may ſignifie the affright and terrour of the evil World at ſo happy a Change, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps alſo, great Commotions raiſed thereon to avoid it, and alſo may further ſignifie the aſtoniſhment of others at it, tho' no Adverſaries to it; and likewiſe the concuſſion it will make in the Body-politick or worldly Fabrick of the Government; which ſeems alſo ſignified by there being <hi>ſlain in the Earthquake</hi> 7000 <hi>Names of Men,</hi> (according to the True T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:37387:18"/> which ſome rightly underſtand Dignities, Offices, and Orders of Men officiating in the Government; and then the ſlaying them will ſignifie their political death, as to their ſo officiating or exerciſing worldly power as before; and the number 7000 ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolically denotes how completely this will be fulfilled; that is, what an abſolute diſſolution will be of their politick-ſtate, and reducing them to a lifeleſs Condition, as to their exerciſing ſuch Power. For as the riſing of the Sun does diſpel the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Night, ſo will all power of darkneſs or worldly power vaniſh, at <hi>the riſing of the Sun of Righteouſneſs upon us,</hi> by the Witneſſes being exalted to that Heaven of power whereto they are called, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But though the Devils power becomes hereby ſo ſuperſeded and determined, as to put an end to his War againſt the Saints, and his exerciſing any Authority againſt the Intereſt of Chriſts Kingdom, yet being not then bound from deceiving the Nations, we are ſtill like to find a continuance of his ill Influence as a deceiver, ſo as much to obſtruct the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs of the Witneſſes in their promoting the Intereſt of that Kingdom, and ſo to make this preludious commencing of it with us to fall much ſhort of its Luſtre that will ſucceed his being bound after the ſeventh Trumpet: So that, the falling of the tenth part of the City ſeems to conſiſt in the ſpirit of Truth gaining the Aſcendent of the Spirit of the World, by the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent of the Witneſſes to Heaven, and ſo transforming us from a Worldly into a Chriſtian ſtate, putting us in a Courſe of managing all Affairs, for the moſt advantagious promoting of Truth and Righteouſneſs, and ſo advancing of Chriſts Kingdom on Earth.</p>
               <p>We having ground from this Viſion ſuddenly to expect ſo happy a Change, as I hope appears from my Expoſition of it, we ought not to be doubtful of it, by reaſon of the ſo little tendency of Affairs yet towards it, through the croſs Influence of carnal Intereſt and worldly Wiſdom being ſo prevalent to obſtruct it: For when ſuch awakening Providences as God hath viſited us with, do ſo little avail to open Mens eyes and turn their hearts to become enlightened with the Wiſdom which is from above, and is revealed by Faith in Him, <hi>in whom are hid all the Treaſures of Wiſdom and Knowledge,</hi> but that they conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue ſtill <hi>not to know, nor will they underſtand, but walk on in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> it betokens ſuch a Change to be nearer at hand, when it
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:37387:18"/> becomes ſo apparent, that God's Work can make no further Advance in the World, than its carried on by his Heavenly Power. And therefore, whenas the preſent diſtracted State of the Nation does ſo much need ſuch a Change for its happy ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement; and alſo, that it's ſo prepared for it as before is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, onely the Spirit of the World continuing predominant, does obſtruct it, and will do ſo whilſt it prevails, How ſhould we doubt but that God will complete the Aſcent of his Riſen Witneſſes to the Heaven of Power, whether they are called? Whereby to give that Turn to the Current of Affairs, as to accompliſh that happy Change which we ſo much need, and are taught by this Viſion ſo ſoon to expect.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="postscript">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:37387:19"/>
               <head>A Poſt-Script.</head>
               <p>THE Late Revolution which the foregoing Diſcourſe makes to be in order to the fulfilling the Fall of the Tenth Part of the City, hath occaſioned a great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt about the Duty of Allegiance, <hi>viz.</hi> Whether it be due to him onely who hath the legal Right to the Throne, though diſpoſſeſt of it, or to the Government or preſent Rul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Power? The great Concern of the Controverſie hath made it ſtrenuouſly managed on both ſides, with much Learning and ſubtle Reaſoning, yet with little ſucceſs in giving ſatisfaction, for want of a due examining the nature and riſe of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which is the Subject of the Controverſie; which doing, is the onely way to put an end to it: For if Monarchical Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is derived from, and does conſiſt in Power, having no Right but what Power gives, (as will appear by examining the Riſe of it) and this Power being of God, no Prince can be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted of it, but by the Concurrence as well as Permiſſion of God, who inveſted him with it, then all Right to the Throne does determine with being outed of the dominion or power of Ruling, and every King <hi>de facto,</hi> is ſo far alſo King <hi>de jure,</hi> and ſo may be obeyed as ſuch.</p>
               <p>The confounding the Patriarchical with the Monarchical Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and making <hi>Adam</hi> to be the firſt Monarch, is ſo ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs a Conceit, that it looks more like a politick Impoſture than a ſerious Opinion or Judgment; the one having no foundation in Nature as the other, and they differing as much as the Relation of Father and Son does from that of Maſter and Servant. And therefore Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> (the chief Champion on the one ſide in this Controverſie) ſays, <hi>That it's evident that there's no natural Authority but the Faternal and Patriarchical Authority, and that Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>rchies
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:37387:19"/> are erected upon the Ruines or great Diminution of it; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hether this was by Conſent, (or as is moſt probable) by violent <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpations, of which</hi> Nimrod <hi>ſeems to have been the firſt Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>e, it's equally unjuſt; for no Authority is ſo ſacred as that which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> natural, which no Man had Authority to give away or uſurp: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ut by this way God erected Monarchies, and gave his Authority <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> them who had none of their own,</hi> Caſ. of Alleg. <hi>p.</hi> 23. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> he rightly makes the riſe of Monarchy to be on the ruines of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e Patriarchical Authority; but then, that this riſe was by vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ent Uſurpations, and if by conſent yet equally unjuſt; and yet, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>at by ſuch means God erected Monarchies, and gave his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hority, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſeems difficult to make out the truth and conſiſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y thereof. And the Dr's way of making ſuch Uſurpations to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e Gods Authority, is ſuch as hath given great Advantages a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt himſelf: For he makes the Uſurper to be Gods Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ity, as ſet up by his Providence, who removeth Kings and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth up Kings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet makes no legal Right to be altered there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>, and ſo makes two concurrent Rights, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> whereby he arms <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s Antagoniſts with ſuch potent Arguments as are not to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ithſtood.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Scruplers Caſe conſidered,</hi> in order to the giving an Account <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f Regal Government, does examine the Original of the two op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite Kingdoms of Chriſt and the Devil in the World: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> he takes a right courſe, if he could but as rightly have proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d in it. He ſuppoſeth <hi>Adam</hi> and his Poſterity to have been ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ed under a Theocracy, and that Man was ſo governed before <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e Flood; and that all deſpotick or tyrannical human Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ents are not founded on any divine Authority, but are the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>rpt Empire of the devil, on his tempting Man to fall from his Allegiance to God. And that this Government being begun in <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ain,</hi> and thoſe who revolted with him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> was after the Flood <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>evived in <hi>Nimrod,</hi> continued ſo by his Succeſſors to <hi>Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>zzar,</hi> and then by the four great Monarchies begun in him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And for deſtroying this Empire of the devil, he makes the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Chriſt to be inſtituted by that Promiſe on <hi>Adams</hi> Fall, <hi>The ſeed of the Woman ſhall break the Serpents Head;</hi> and that thereby Chriſt was then veſted in the Authority of the Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cracy, and hath exerciſed the ſame both before and ſince his aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming our Nature, by human Governments reformed by Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Laws; Whereby thoſe Governments which had ſo miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:37387:20"/> a riſe, deſtructive of Mankind, the goodneſs of God turned to a Bleſſing, condeſcending therein to our lapſed ſtate, which could not bear the awful Soveraignty of the Theocracy united to our innocent ſtate. And ſuch reformed humane Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments, by which Chriſt exerciſeth the ſaid Authority of the Theocracy, he maketh onely to be irreſiſtible, as having the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Authority, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Which Account does Right, neither to the Kingdom of the devil nor of Chriſt, detracting from the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the one, and the Spirituality of the other.</p>
               <p>That the Kingdom of the devil is the Authority of God, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be gain-ſaid, without doing much Violence to Scripture: His claim to the Kingdoms of the World, <hi>as delivered to him to give to whom he will,</hi> Luk. 4.6. our Saviour does not gainſay, and does oft own him as Prince of this World, by giving him that Title, and ſpeaking of his Kingdom as Prince thereof. Which ſurely he would not have done, if the devil were not Prince there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of by Authority, but onely by Uſurpation. And to imagine that the devil could advance himſelf to that ſtation, without God's authorizing him thereunto by his concurrence, ſavours of that Epicurean Spirit which excludes Gods Providence from govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the World. For if the devil exerciſeth ſo great dominion by Uſurpation, and not under God, by his Authority, his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is ſo far excluded as the devil's does extend. But God does rule in all the powers of darkneſs, and they exerciſe no power but by Him, as our Saviour tells <hi>Pilate, Thou couldſt have no power againſt me except it was given thee from above.</hi> For though they yield no voluntary obedience by obſerving his Laws, yet they are under his Government and Reſtraint, in the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of that power wherewith they purſue their wicked Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Whereby he makes them Inſtruments of fulfilling his will when they rebel againſt Him. And the Heavenly ſtation of power which the devil poſſeſt in the Heathen Empire of <hi>Rome</hi> deſcribed, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12. <hi>by a great red Dragon in Heaven, having ſeven Heads and ten Horns, and ſeven Crowns on his Heads,</hi> &amp;c. does ſhew his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion to be by Authority, and not by Uſurpation; as alſo does the reviving of his Kingdom in the Ten-horned-beaſt, <hi>cap.</hi> 13. <hi>To whom he gave his Power and Seat and great Authority.</hi> And though the dominion of the deſpotick Rulers under him, is by this Author but his uſurpt Empire: yet by the Scripture it's the Authority of God, as appears by what is ſaid of <hi>Cyrus,</hi> Eſa. 45.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:37387:20"/> and by <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> being told by <hi>Daniel, That God had given him a Kingdom, Power, Strength and Glory,</hi> cap. 2.37. and by his being called God's Servant, into whoſe hands he gave the Nations <hi>&amp;c. Jer.</hi> 27.6. So that, though this Author will allow ſuch Rulers to reign but by God's permiſſion, yet they are au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorized thereunto by his concurrence to their advancement, as will after more fully appear.</p>
               <p>But it ſeems to this Author a Reflexion on the divine Juſtice and Goodneſs, to make ſuch deſtructive Rulers God's Authority; but it will not appear ſo, if we look on them as Miniſters of his wrath, <hi>whom he hath ordained for Judgment and eſtabliſhed for Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</hi> And therefore it's ſtrange that this Author ſhould allow a deſtructive power to be of God's appointment for puniſhment, and that therefore, <hi>though it's not irreſiſtible upon the account of divine Authority, yet it's to be born with till God accompliſh his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure on thoſe he ſcourges with it,</hi> p. 29. and yet, that he ſhould not allow ſuch power to be God's Authority, tho' ſo appointed by Him for the exerciſing that power (given by him to that end) on thoſe who by following their own waies, become meet to reap ſuch fruit of their doings. For whenas the Wickedneſs of the old World was ſo great as to make <hi>God repent that he made Man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n the Earth,</hi> and therefore to deſtroy that World; and inſtead of Reformation, the new World became immerſed deeper in corruption, (God deſiſting from further ſtriving by his Spirit with ſinful Fleſh, as he had done with the old World, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.3.) though He would not deſtroy it again as before, by reaſon of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ppy end he deſigned to put to the wicked and miſerable ſtate of it, by his coming, <hi>Who ſhould make Reconciliation for Iniquity, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd bring in everlaſting Righteouſneſs;</hi> yet till then, as the World <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>as become more lyable to death (which is the Wages of Sin) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>an the old World, ſo it was ſubjected to him <hi>Who hath the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>r of death committed to him, thro' fear of which he makes men <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> their life time ſubject to bondage,</hi> under ſuch deſtructive powers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> govern onely by ſerpentine wiſdom or worldly policy, for ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>fying their Ambition and other boundleſs Luſts. Hence the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ur Beaſts ſignifying the four great Monarchies, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. do ariſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>t of the Sea, as alſo does the Ten-horned-beaſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. &amp; in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>p. 17.8. &amp; <hi>cap.</hi> 11.7. he aſcends out of the Bottomleſs-pit, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> alſo do the Locuſts ſignifying the Saracen Empire come thence, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>p.</hi> 9. Which Sea and Bottomleſs-pit denote the Spirit of domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:37387:21"/> in worldly Rulers, acted by the Spirit of the world un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Prince thereof, and the Abyſs of inſatiable Luſts they are ſunk into, whereby they overflow and overwhelm the world in Thraldom under the bondage of Corruption; being upheld in ſuch domination by thoſe <hi>Floods of ungodly Men,</hi> who are the power of Hell, or of that <hi>Spirit which worketh in the Children of Diſobedience,</hi> and thereby become <hi>the Waters that make great, and the deep that ſets on high,</hi> thoſe Rulers in their deſpotick do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion. Hence he, under whom they thus rule, is called <hi>Levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>athan the piercing crooked Serpent, and the Dragon that is in the Sea,</hi> Eſa. 27.1. and the deſtroying his dominion is ſignified by, <hi>There ſhall be no more Sea,</hi> Rev. 21.1.</p>
               <p>Since therefore Man by Apoſtacy became ſubject to Apoſtate Angels, <hi>thoſe Principalities and Powers, and Rulers of the darkneſs of this World, &amp;c.</hi> who gave riſe to the unnatural deſpotick dominion, whereby to eſtabliſh the Kingdom of darkneſs in the World, it's evident that worldly Rulers under thoſe powers, can have no Authority or Right to rule, but what is founded on their Power, that is, their Right is their Power which they gain over lapſed Mankind, which by falling from God's Rule over them, or deſerting their Obedience to Him, become ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted of him, and given over to the Miniſters of his wrath, whoſe Power is not uſurpt by God's permiſſion, (which, as ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before, does claſh with his providence as Governour of the World) but is given to them by Him, for fulfilling his Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Will on thoſe, who by revolting from Him, become meet to be ſubjected to ſuch Rulers. For how wicked ſoever are the inclinations of ſuch Rulers, yet they continue ſo under the rule of God's power, when faln from his moral rule over them, as not to be able to commit any evil without his concurrence, by giving way or letting them looſe thereunto, whereby he is the Author of the deed done, though not of the evil committed in the doing it. As when wild Beaſts let looſe by their Kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers commit deſtruction, though it be wholly their deed, yet the Keeper by reaſon of his letting them looſe is an Author thereof.</p>
               <p>But God does further concur in the Advancing of worldly Rulers to dominion, by aiding them with His Power, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing if from them outed by them. Whence he is ſaid to gird and looſe the Loyns of Princes, when he does inveſt them
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:37387:21"/> with Power, and deveſt them thereof. Thus did <hi>He gird</hi> Cyrus <hi>though he had not known him;</hi> and having inveſted him thus with Power (by reaſon of which he is called <hi>Gods Anointed to ſubdue Nations,</hi> &amp;c.) <hi>He looſed the Loins of Kings before him,</hi> Eſa. 45.5.1. And when he deveſted <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> of his Power, it's ſaid to him from Heaven, <hi>Thy Kingdom is departed from thee;</hi> and when he re-inveſted him with it, <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> ſaies not onely, <hi>My rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon returned to me,</hi> but alſo, <hi>For the glory of my Kingdom, my Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Brightneſs returned to me, and my Counſellors and Lords ſought unto me, and I was eſtabliſhed in my Kingdom, and excellent Majesty was added to me,</hi> Dan. 4. And of God's inveſting Princes thus with Power, and again deveſting them thereof, ſpeaks <hi>Job, cap.</hi> 12. <hi>ver.</hi> 18, 19. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And whereas rightful legal Princes are agreed to be the Power of God, how could they be outed by thoſe who are called Uſurpers, if they were not of God alſo? Unleſs that Power which is not of God can prevail againſt that which is of him. And therefore, though <hi>Baaſh</hi> did conſpire againſt his rightful Prince and ſlay him, and reign in his ſtead, yet it's ſaid, <hi>That God did exalt him out of the duſt, and make him Prince over his People,</hi> 1 Kings, <hi>cap.</hi> 15. <hi>ver.</hi> 27. 28. <hi>cap.</hi> 16. <hi>ver.</hi> 1. 2. And the ſame muſt be agreed to in the Caſe of <hi>Athaliah,</hi> &amp;c. So that, though legal Right or Title be ſo much inſiſted on, to make a Prince the Authority of God, or a rightful Ruler, yet indeed it does not give right, and ſo make the Prince that hath it, the Authority of God, but helps to preſerve and defend him in that Power and Authority which God gives, as mens natural rights are not given, but preſerved and defended by Law.</p>
               <p>For as the abounding of Fraud and Violence, did make poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Laws needful for ſecuring mens Rights and Properties, ſo Worldly Rulers, through their oppreſſive dominion, and male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adminiſtration of Government, do make themſelves ſo uneaſie to their Subjects, as to find it needful to betake themſelves to what ſecurity human policy can yield. Hence proceeds Oaths of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance, and Declarations, and Confirmations of their Rights and Titles by publick Acts of ſtate, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which, though they may be of ſome uſe for their more quiet ſettlement whilſt it pleaſeth God to continue them in their dominion, yet confer no Right which can continue, after their being ſtript of the power that did exalt them to the Throne. To which they could not have aſcended, but by the Concurrence and Aid of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:37387:22"/> God, as aforeſaid, which is as full a manifeſtion of his Will, as an expreſs declaration of it could be; and therefore, as ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual to give right to him that is advanc'd, and determine his right that is outed thereby.</p>
               <p>It may be Objected, That Monarchs by election do thereby re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a right from the People to rule, whereby their dominion does not conſiſt only in power, but is founded alſo on right. To which I ſay, That ſuch Monarchs receive their power or authority from the People by their Election, no more than the chief Magiſtrate of a Corporation receives his from thoſe who elect him; but as he derives the ſame from the ſupreme power of the Nation, whoſe Miniſter he is, though elected by the Corporation, ſo ſuch elective Monarchs derive their power and authority from, and are Miniſters of the ſupreme ruling powers of the World, <hi>viz.</hi> of the devil, as Prince thereof, and of God, as ſuperintending the adminiſtration of that power committed to him. So that, there can be no deveſting ſuch Monarchs of their power, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out that concurrence of providence, as will alſo determine their right to rule; and the uſe of ſuch Elections is not to give Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to rule, but to make a more happy Government, by a good harmony between Rulers and People, which is like to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from ſuch conſent and choice. Beſides, Elective Monarchy is improperly reputed Monarchical Government, that properly importing ſuch abſolute dominion as prevailed in the Heathen World, and does ſtill ſo in Heathen and Mahometan Kingdoms. But in the Infancy of it, before the Corruptions of the World and the Deluſions of the devil, advanc'd it to ſuch a height, it retained ſome mixture of the Patriarchical Government, on the ruines of which it was founded, whereby the People retained ſome freedom and intereſt in the Government by choice of their Rulers, which they were after deprived of by the prevailing power of the devil; and which they have in ſome meaſure re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gained, by that declenſion of his power which Chriſtianity hath introduced; of which I have ſpoken in the preceding diſcourſe, and which is ſignified by the Feet and Toes of the great Image, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2. being <hi>partly iron and partly clay,</hi> typifying the Roman Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire its becoming divided into ten Kingdoms, (as it was ſoon after its becoming Chriſtian) and becoming then <hi>partly ſtrong and partly broken,</hi> or brittle. Which broken power of the devil is at length abſolutely to be deſtroyed, by <hi>that Kingdom which the God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:37387:22"/> ſhall ſet up, and which ſhall never be deſtroyed, but ſhall break in pieces and conſume all theſe Kingdoms, and ſhall ſtand for ever,</hi> ver. 44.</p>
               <p>Alſo the Objections which are ſtrongly urged againſt Dr.<hi>Sher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock,</hi> become invalid from what I have ſaid: For firſt, there can be no want of legal Title to him that hath all the right that ſuch Title can give, <hi>viz.</hi> That hath the power of God which gave riſe to ſuch Title; and therefore that Title will little a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail the outed Prince, to whom the Dr. leaves it unaltered by a rightful King ſet up by Providence, and ſo makes two concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent rights, as before noted. Nor Secondly, can the poſſeſſing of a Throne thus by Providence, be parallell'd with a Thief or Robber's poſſeſſing a Purſe by providence, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For there's not the like concurrence of providence in the latter caſe as in the former, where God withdraws his power from him who is diſpoſſeſt, and aids him with it who is advanc'd, as before ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, without which he could not have ſo prevailed. And yet there's that concurrence of providence in the latter caſe, by giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing way to thoſe Thieves and Robbers, and letting them looſe, as aforeſaid, to purſue their wicked Inclinations, as may ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fee to make one the Authority of God, who is advanced to rule by ſuch concurrence of providence; it appearing thereby, that God does not onely permit, but alſo will the event or ſucceſs, though not the wicked means uſed for the obtaining it. And Thirdly, that Inference from the Dr's. Aſſertion (which he knows not how to yield to, nor well to quit himſelf of it, <hi>viz.</hi>) that <hi>Cromwel</hi> and the other powers that prevailed in thoſe times, will then be God's Authority, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> muſt from what hath been ſaid, be yielded to without ſcruple. And indeed, they were more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly the Authority of God, than the legal power they prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt. For that was but mediately his Authority as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to rule according to the courſe of the governments of the World under the Prince thereof; but thoſe powers that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed againſt it, were ſet up by the immediate interpoſition of providence, for preſerving and promoting the intereſt of Chriſts Kingdom, againſt thoſe Antichriſtian deſigns driven on, which involved the Nation in war, as appears by the preceding diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe. And if thoſe powers were not thus ſet up of God, but were wicked Uſurpations, they muſt be of the devil; and for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>im to interrupt and ſubvert his ordinary courſe of government,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:37387:23"/> by ſuch changes as tend to the advancing of Chriſts Kingdom, and ſo to the leſſening his own power, would be like <hi>Satans caſting out Satan, and how then can his Kingdom ſtand?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Its wonder therefore that Dr. <hi>Sherlock,</hi> who tells us, <hi>That the increaſe and deſtruction of the Kingdom of Antichriſt is to be accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh'd by great Changes and Revolutions in human governments,</hi> p. 22. ſhould ſo ſeverely cenſure the tranſactions of thoſe Civil Wars, and not look upon them to be alike Works of Providence for promoting the ruine of Antichriſt, whenas they gave ſo great a check to the Antichriſtian deſigns then driven on, and ſuch ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance to the intereſt of Chriſt's Kingdom, as that when, by the turn of affairs, thoſe deſigns were more eagerly than ever pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued, and that with greater advantage than ever, both from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad and at home, to make the ſame ſucceſsful, yet all hath proved like <hi>the Rain deſcending, and the Floods coming, and the Winds blowing and beating on a Houſe ſounded on a Rick,</hi> his Kingdom having ſo emerged above all oppoſition, as to be now near a triumphant ſtate in this Nation. But it appearing by the Dr's Preface, that the Liberty of Thoughts he hath taken, proceeds from the Authority of Biſhop <hi>Overals</hi> Convocation book, which <hi>freed him from the apprehenſions of Singularity and Novelty which he was cramp't with,</hi> he could hardly take greater freedom than the Authority of that Book gave; eſpecially, in Affairs, wherein he is alſo crampt with a great prejudice, which occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned his ſo crippling the Truth he aſſerts, in not giving it its due ſcope or extent, and thereby giving ſuch advantage againſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf as before noted.</p>
               <p>But whereas on Profanation of the Temple by <hi>Antiochus Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanes,</hi> it's ſaid <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.32. <hi>The People that know their God ſhall be ſtrong and do Exploits,</hi> meaning the Reſiſtance made by the <hi>Maccabees,</hi> may not thoſe Exploits (which are there ſpoken of with approbation) be lyable to be cenſured, as the Dr. does the Actions of the late Times, by the ſame meaſure wherewith he judgeth them? For the one was a reſiſting Authority as much as the other, yea and more, as being begun by private Subjects, whereas the other was a Conflict of Authority with it ſelf, or of one part of the Legiſlative power with the other, and that upon urgent occaſion given, though it be called by the Dr. <hi>A bare-fac'd Rebellion,</hi> p. 46 And may not thoſe <hi>called choſen and faithful, wherewith the Lamb overcomes the Kings of the Earth
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:37387:23"/> that war with him,</hi> Rev. 14. <hi>and thoſe Armies on White Horſes in Heaven, following him that is faithful and true, and in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſs doth judge and make War,</hi> cap. 19.11. I ſay, may, or ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot theſe Powers of Chriſt to ſettle him in his Kingdom on Earth, be lyable, by the ſame meaſure, to the like Cenſures with thoſe of the Dr.? For they will not have the Authority of worldly powers to bear them out, for thoſe they are to war a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, as withſtanding the ſettling of Chriſt in his Kingdom; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd therefore muſt act upon his Authority, to whoſe ſervice, through faith and knowledge of Him, they have devoted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. And ſo not being authorized by the viſible worldly po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers, will be lyable to be cenſured, as the Dr. does thoſe of the late Times, by the blind world, that judgeth onely according to outer Appearance. It's evident therefore, that through Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God and Faith in Him, there may be ſuch a diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and reſiſtance of worldly Rulers by their Subjects, as is righteous in his ſight, and acceptable ſervice to Him, however condemned of Men. So that, as the whole project of Antichriſt is, under the guiſe of a Chriſtian Profeſſion to ſubvert Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, ſo the Doctrine of Non-reſiſtance, as it hath been mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by many, is a playing the like game; that is, under the Colour of teaching the pure Chriſtian Doctrine of Paſſive Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, to deter Men from being concerned in the great works of Providence againſt the powers of the World, for the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Chriſt's Kingdom therein, and ſo, as much as may be, to obſtruct the coming thereof.</p>
               <p>Since therefore the deſpotick dominion of worldly Rulers, is but the Empire of the devil, which be gave riſe to by tempting Man to fall, and which Chriſt came to deſtroy by deſtroying the works of the devil, thoſe bands of corruption which linkt ſinful Man to the Thraldom of his power, it appears how in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable Men are of, and unmeet for Liberty, whilſt they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue the Servants of ſin, and that there's no true Freedom but that wherewith Chriſt does make them free; no Laws (though they be ſo much conſided in) being any ſecurity for Mens Rights and Liberties, whilſt the dominion of ſin in them, does make them the Vaſſals of Satan, <hi>taken captive by him at his will.</hi> And therefore thoſe forms of Government which make a Nation re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted a Free People, do little avail thereto, further than they preſerve them from being ſo deeply immerſed in corruptions
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:37387:24"/> as other Nations, and ſo make them retain ſome vigour and ſtrength to maintain their Rights and Liberties. Hence it hath been a policy of deſpotick Rulers, to corrupt their People by licentious Liberty, whereby to make them more firmly their ſlaves; they being thereby diſperited to ſtruggle for Freedom, and are made in love with Thraldom. As the <hi>Cappadocians</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a more vicious Nation than any other, did refuſe the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of being made a Free People when offered it by the <hi>Romans;</hi> no liberty being regarded by ſuch People, but that of ſerving their Luſts that reign in them; whereby that Government is moſt pleaſing to them, that does moſt indulge them <hi>in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Servants of Sin and free from Righteouſneſs, the bands of which they would break and caſt away the cords thereof from them.</hi> And when Men by Apoſtacy from God, become ſo degenerated into Enmity againſt Him, that is, againſt Truth and Righteouſneſs, they are fit Sbujects for the domination of ſuch Powers, as will have as little regard to the ſame in ruling over them, but deal with them according the bruitiſh ſtate they are ſunk into.</p>
               <p>The proper end indeed of all worldly powers, is become the <hi>Ministers of God for good, by being a terrour to evil and not to good works;</hi> and in ſome meaſure they uſually prove ſo, human policy or worldly wiſdom moving them to reſtrain great Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes in wickedneſſes. But when ſuch heroical Princes are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced to rule, as moſt purſue the due ends of Government, yet all that they can effect is but like palliating Cures. The in-ſide is firſt to be cleanſed, that the out-ſide may be clean al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo; whilſt the Corruptions of ſinful Fleſh remain unpurg'd, they will have their courſe of evil Operations: Till men have found the ſtrait paths of Life, they will be ſtraggling in the broad ways of deſtruction; and whilſt they are thus held with the cords of their ſins, there's no freeing them from the Thral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Satan: There's no recovering them from that bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage of Corruption, but by that redemption which ſaves them from their ſins, and makes them free by the Truth, and ſo <hi>delivers them from the power of darkneſs, and tranſlates them into the Kingdom of our Lord.</hi> The power of the devil muſt be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, by deſtroying his works that gave riſe to it. This there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore being the end of Chriſt's Kingdom coming on Earth, How deſireable are all Advancements of it in the world! And how delightful ought to be ſuch Tokens of its approaching, as our
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:37387:24"/> Saviour ſpeaks of, <hi>When theſe things begin to come to paſs, look up and lift up your heads, for your Redemption draweth near, and when you ſee theſe things come to paſs, the Kingdom of God is nigh at hand,</hi> Luk. 21. <hi>ver.</hi> 28. 31. Wherefore, my preceding Expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion giving an Account of a preludious commencing of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in this Nation being at hand, to end our preſent Troubles and Diſtractions, in a ſtate of Chriſtian Peace and Liberty, by diſſolution of all oppoſite power thereto; it muſt ſurely be a welcome diſcovery to all who are ſo much Friends to the Truth, as to deſire that it may prove true; for they, I hope, will ſee ſufficient reaſon to perſwade them of the Truth of it.</p>
               <p>Whereas I ſaid, that the Author of the Scruplers Caſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, does detract from the Spirituality of Chriſt's Kingdom, as well as from the Authority of the devils Kingdom, I ſhall now give ſome brief Account of it, though it not much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns the purpoſe of my Poſt-ſcript. His ſuppoſing <hi>Adam</hi> and his Poſterity to have been ſettled under a Theocracy, and that Man was ſo governed before the Flood, may be allowed, mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereby, that he was not governed then by any human Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment ſet up by politick Laws, but by the Law of Nature, or Law of God written in Mans Heart; by which Law the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal or Patriarchical Authority was exerciſed. But he is much out in further ſuppoſing, that the putting the Government into the hands of one of our own nature, by the aforeſaid promiſe on <hi>Adams</hi> Fall, was <hi>a Condeſcention to our lapſed ſtate, which could not bear the awful Soveraignty of a Theocracy annexed to our innocent ſtate,</hi> as if Chriſt's Kingdom was inferiour to the Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cracy annext to that ſtate, whenas indeed it's much ſuperiour to the ſame. For <hi>Adam</hi> in innocency was but in a natural car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ſtate; he was a <hi>natural</hi> Adam, <hi>or living Soul, of the Earth earthly;</hi> but the ſecond <hi>Adam, the Lord from Heaven being a quickning Spirit,</hi> came to bring that ſpiritual Theocracy, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation of divine Life, which is the coming of the Kingdom of Heaven on Earth; whereby Chriſt does rule in believers, and is by them to rule the world, and which was not known to the world, till revealed by the <hi>Prince of Life, who brought Life and Immortality to light by the Goſpel:</hi> It was before <hi>the hidden wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God, ordained before the World unto our Glory, ehe Myste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries hid from Ages and Generations, but now made manifeſt to the Saints,</hi> Col. 1.26. hid from the Prophets that propheſied of it,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:37387:25"/> and the Angels that deſired to look into it, 1 <hi>Pet. Chap.</hi> 1.</p>
               <p>Whereas therefore this Author, makes not onely Chriſts King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to be inſtituted by the aforeſaid promiſe on <hi>Adams</hi> Fall, but alſo him thereby to be veſted in his Authority, and to have exerciſed the ſame in human Governments, reformed by righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Laws, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> both before and ſince his aſſuming our Nature; and alſo does aſcribe ſo much Vertue to Faith in Him, before his coming, as that <hi>it was ſufficient to free Men from that Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of Nature wherein the ſpiritual dominion of the Devil did conſiſt, and to reunite them by a holy Nature to the Father of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits,</hi> p. 22. He ſeems to have little Knowledge of that ſpiritual diſpenſation, which the coming of Chriſt did introduce, and thereby commence the Kingdom of Heaven on Earth. For Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers in Chriſt before his coming, <hi>dyed in Faith, not having received the Promiſes, but having ſeen them afar off, and were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded of them and embraced them,</hi> &amp;c. So that, tho' they might joy in the perſwaſion of ſo happy a State to come, yet they did it without knowing what it would be, as Men joy in belief of a happy State in the other Life, without knowing what it will be; and therefore ſurely could not find ſuch happy effects from Belief of it, till revealed by his coming. For whenas <hi>we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding as in a glaſs, the Glory of the Lord, are changed into the ſame Image from Glory to Glory,</hi> &amp;c. So that, <hi>the Righteouſneſs of God revealed in us from Faith to Faith in Him,</hi> is wrought in us by contemplating the manifeſtation of God in Him, How could this be till he was made known to the world, or became <hi>God manifeſted in the Fleſh?</hi> There was therefore before, no ſuch Vertue of Faith in Him for renewing our Nature, and freeing Men from the Corruption of it, as this Author imagines; nor any Reformation by righteous Laws, but what is competent to politick worldly Governments, where the Spirit of the world will prevail in the modalizing them, and ſo make the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation by ſuch Laws amount to no more than his Government, who when he finds it for the Intereſt of his Kingdom, can <hi>tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form himſelf into an Angel of Light, and his Miniſters into Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Righteouſneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And there were ſome Heathen Emperours, who muſt be grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be worldly Powers under the Prince of this world, that yet will put in for Rulers, by whom Chriſt did exerciſe his Authority of the Theocracy, according to this Authors Account
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:37387:25"/> thereof. But no Reformation by righteous Laws can amount to the Theocracy of Chriſt's Kingdom, without the concurrence of that Spiritual Power which is the Life of all ſuch Laws, and wherein the dominion of Chriſt's Kingdom, or the Kingdom of Heaven which he brought on Earth, does conſiſt; we being there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by enabled to act according to the Judgments of Truth contrary to the Spirit of the World, and ſo, to overcome the World, and advance the Kingdom of Heaven on Earth. And yet this Author ſeems ſcarce to have higher conceptions of the State of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in its perfection, than what he imagines of it before and ſince Chriſt's coming. For he calls the <hi>Millennium, Thoſe happy times, when by means of Chriſt's viſible Miniſters the World ſhall be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to ſo peaceable a condition, as will be proper for putting down all other Rule and Authority but his own, and ſubjecting all things im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately to himſelf,</hi> p. 23. but no mention of that ſpiritual do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion wherewith he ſhall then reign. So that, by thoſe happy times he ſeems onely to underſtand a Chriſtian Common-wealth, wherein the former worldly ſtate of Government ſhall be put down, and the Saints ſhall rule onely by Chriſt's Laws, but he ſeems not aware of that diſpenſation which onely can enable to fulfil his Laws, and which is ſignified by <hi>The Tabernacle of God being with men, and his dwelling with them, and the New Jeruſalem not needing the Sun or Moon to ſhine into it, having the Glory of God and the Lamb to be the light thereof, and the Throne of God and the Lamb in it, and by their eating of the Tree of Life, and drinking of the Waters of Life freely,</hi> &amp;c. And it's Chriſt's re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing the World to an immediate ſubjection to himſelf, that muſt introduce that peaceable ſtate which this Author imagines the World ſhall be reſtored to, to prepare it for his immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Rule; and thoſe viſible Miniſters by whom he ſuppoſeth ſuch preparation to be made, muſt be his Miniſters in human Governments, and ſo are more likely to oppoſe than make pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration for his immediate Rule, by which they ſhall be put down.</p>
               <p>This Author therefore, by aſcribing ſo much Vertue to Faith in Chriſt before his coming, both for bettering human Nature and human Governments, and by making ſuch Governments re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by righteous Laws, to be the Theocracy of Chriſt's King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, he does in effect reduce the ſpiritual diſpenſation of that Kingdom into a ſtate of legal Righteouſneſs, of living accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:37387:26"/> to the Precepts of the Goſpel, without the aid of that Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer which onely can enable us to do it, and ſo, with many Chriſtian Profeſſors, does ſtumble at the Righteouſneſs of God by Faith, in like manner as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> are deſcribed to have done, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.32.33. <hi>cap.</hi> 10.2.3. And his conceits of Chriſts and the devils Kingdom in the other World, are as odd as thoſe of their ſtate in this World.</p>
               <p>For he makes the uſurp't Authority of the devil, to be ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual in the other World over the Souls of men, as well as tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral in this, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and makes the Fighting of <hi>Michael</hi> and his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and the Devil and his Angels, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12. to ſignifie the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual War in the other World, between the oppoſite Powers of Chriſt and the devil, for the dominion over Souls, <hi>p.</hi> 21. whenas doubtleſs it ſignifies, the War that enſued between the Chriſtian and Pagan Emperours, and other Champions for Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganiſm, on the former profeſſing Chriſtianity, which produced the great Revolution deſcribed in the ſixth Seal, ſpoken of in the preceding diſcourſe. And it appears not that the devil hath any concern with Souls, further than to corrupt them with his deceits and allurements of this Life, whereby to ſecure them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Thraldom, and ſo to ſtrengthen his Kingdom in the World. And Chriſt does withſtand and oppoſe the ſame, by the counter-working of his Spirit, by which he deſtroys the works of the devil, and is at length to ſubdue all things to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: And to imagine any ſuch War for dominion over Souls, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct from what is tranſacted between thoſe oppoſite powers in this Life, by the Conflict between Fleſh and Spirit, is an unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable Conceit.</p>
               <p>But this Author, in thus attempting to give an Account of Riſe of the Kingdom of Chriſt and the devil in the World, hath hit upon the propereſt courſe for ending our great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies about the Duty of Allegiance to Worldly Powers. For when it appears, That their Power or Authority hath no foundation in Nature, and ſo cannot be conſidered as thoſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties that are founded on natural Right, but is derived from, and exerciſed under him, who by ſeducing man into like Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate State with himſelf, at length obtained the dominion over him; and that as God did give him that Power for correcting and diſciplining by Thraldom, thoſe who would not be kept in Obedience to <hi>Him whoſe Service is perfect Freedom;</hi> ſo he does
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:37387:26"/> enlarge and ſtraiten it, and otherwaies govern and controul him in the exerciſe of it, as beſt ſerves the ends for which he gave it: So that, no Changes or weighty Affairs of Government can be tranſacted without his Concurrence who thus ſuperintends the adminiſtration of that Power he gives, Theſe Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations will remove all doubt concerning the Right to the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Allegiance, when it's apparent where the Ruling Power reſides; eſpecially, in caſe of ſuch Changes as are for the eaſe and relief of People from their oppreſſive Thraldom; for they muſt proceed from the interpoſing Providence of God, as ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as the devil will have no hand in the leſſening his own Power. And therefore, How can we doubt of our late great Revolution proceeding thence, having already found ſuch hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py effects of it, and having ſuch grounds of hopes of much greater, from that fulfilling the Fall of the Tenth Part of the City, which the preceding Expoſition gives an Account of?</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 32. line 17, for, <hi>is become,</hi> read <hi>is to become.</hi> Pag. 4. lin. 39. for <hi>—Ius the,</hi> read <hi>—lus; The</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
